<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A corosyfe to be layed hard vnto the hartes of all faythfull professours of Christes Gospel. Gathered out of the scriptures by Iohn Ra[m]sey</title>
            <title>Corosyfe to be layed hard unto the hartes of all faythfull professours of Christes Gospel.</title>
            <author>Ramsay, John, 1496?-1551.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1548</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 11 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10385</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20661</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S104467</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99840205</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99840205</idno>
            <idno type="VID">4681</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10385)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 4681)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 140:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A corosyfe to be layed hard vnto the hartes of all faythfull professours of Christes Gospel. Gathered out of the scriptures by Iohn Ra[m]sey</title>
                  <title>Corosyfe to be layed hard unto the hartes of all faythfull professours of Christes Gospel.</title>
                  <author>Ramsay, John, 1496?-1551.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>W. Hill,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1548?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A (A8 blank).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church of England --  Doctrines --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:4681:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 71 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:4681:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 71 -->
            <p>¶ A Coroſyfe <hi>TO BE LAYED HARD</hi> vnto the hartes of all faythfull Profeſſours of Chriſtes Goſpel. Gathered out of the ſcriptures by Iohn Ra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſey.</p>
            <p>☜ ⚜ ☞</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Mathew. vi.</bibl>
               <p>Fyrſt ſeke the Kyngdom of God and al thynges ſhalbe myniſtred vnto you,</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Actes. iii<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</bibl>
               <p>There is no helth in none other but onely in Ieſus Chriſte.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Mathew. ix.</bibl> 
               <p>The whole nedeth no Phiſitian.</p>
            </q>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:4681:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 72 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:4681:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 72 -->
            <head>¶ A Coriſyffe to be Layde, harde vnto the hartes of al fay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thefull Profeſſours of Chryſtes Goſpell. Gathered out of the Scriptures by Iohn Ramſey.</head>
            <p>BRetheren ye knowe we be all baptiſed in Chriſte Ieſu And haue Profeſſed to bee,<note place="margin">Roma. vi. Gala. iii.</note> hys ſouldyers, and he for to bee but Capytayne,<note place="margin">Pſal. i. Ephe. i. Pet. ii.</note> and hathe lefte vs and enſample, bothe in worde and lyuynge, ſpreadynge abrode the banner of hys precyous bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy vpon the mount of Caluary,<note place="margin">Iohn. i<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Collo, <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> proclaimynge hys <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ictorye a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſte all hys enemies ſaiyng Conſummatum eſt, all is Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fourmed or ended,<note place="margin">Luke. xi<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> and there brough to ſubiection to be hys priſoners bothe ſynne death and Hell, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all theyre powers,<note place="margin">mat. xxvii.</note> try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphyng as a valiente conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour,
<pb facs="tcp:4681:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 73 -->ſo that the powers of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen dyd quake, the Sunne and Moue loſte their lyghtes,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, 1</note> affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mynge it was he and none other (but Ieſu Chryſte (able to paci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy the fathers wrath. They <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of the Garthe al<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o moued ſtones dyd breake,<note place="margin">Mat. xvii</note> the b<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dyes that wer buryed dyd ryſe out of theyr graues, acknoweleginge he was the victorious Prynce that ſhould redeme all the fleſhe of the world from eternall dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacyon and to brynge them to hys euerlaſtyng kyndome,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> there for to rainge with God hys fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther eternally.<note place="margin">i. Cor. i. Iohn,</note> And in this vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant and tryumphaunt conqueſt he gaue ouer hys life, to be kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen vnto vs for euermore to be our chefe Lorde, oure chefe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demer, our chefe Aduocate, and that for euer more,<note place="margin">Ephe. i. 1. Pet. 1.</note> Ande for that we woulde counte him iuſte not
<pb facs="tcp:4681:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 73 -->forſakyng vs,<note place="margin">Actes. iii.</note> on the thyrd daye he roſe from death to lyfe to con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>forte vs in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>itle ouer y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whyche he had made vs Lordes.<note place="margin">Iohn. <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>vi</note>
            </p>
            <p>Concludi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g withe vs, it was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedt not for hym to go his waye,<note place="margin">Actes. ii<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> (&amp; that vnto his father) ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dyng vs the holy Ghoſte f<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> be our conductoure in euery ſkirme or conflict. And ſo accordi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fourmed the ſame.<note place="margin">Philip. ii,</note> And at the ty<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me of his departynge both God and man did aſſend vp into he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">Hebre. x Pſal. c. lxc</note> vntyll thoſe (whiche yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayn his enemies) be made his foteſtole, geuyng vs a commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dacione that he woulde come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayn and iudge <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">Actes. x<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> who had bene a faythfull ſouldier in hys abſens.<note place="margin">i. Cor xii</note> And to rewarde bothe them and other accordyng<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lye.<note place="margin">In the god<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly, ſong qui cunque</note> Eythere euerlaſtynge ioye, or els perpetuall Dampnacyon.
<pb facs="tcp:4681:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 74 -->Nowe dere brethren laye thys Coriſyffe hard home to your co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences.<note place="margin">Philip. ii.</note> And fele whether ye be trewe ſouldiors to youre maſter Chryſt or no,<note place="margin">Mat. xiii.</note> thynke whether ye faint or no,<note place="margin">Luk. xxii.</note> when any man dothe inuade your Kyngdome contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to youre chefe captayns com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement.<note place="margin">Mark. xiii</note> Fele whether ye be ſtronge whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Satha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doth aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſault you with ſharpe temptaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,<note place="margin">Luke. xiii</note> loke whether ye be ſicke or feble to endure the ſtormes of trybulacyon,<note place="margin">Ephe. vi. Math. x,</note> proue and taſte youre manlynes, whether it be not turned to cowardenes, and dayly ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne away do ye not leaue in time of nede y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> croſſe of Chriſt (youre battell axe) behinde you for feare.<note place="margin">Iohn. xi</note> Do ye not ſe youre ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moure rouſt, couered wyth the vayne thynges of worldly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire?<note place="margin">Expo. xvi.</note> ſtande not youre ſtoma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes agaynſt Chryſtes Goſpell?
<pb facs="tcp:4681:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 74 -->and woulde gladly haue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fleſhe pottes of Egipt agayn?<note place="margin">Luke. xii,</note> And do ye perceyue your ſelues to be vy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gila<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in prayer nyghte and daye, leſt youre ennemies fall ſodei<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly vpon you? Are ye circunſpect in youre liuynges to honour youre Lord god aryght?<note place="margin">deut. xviii</note> Do ye not for get youre duety to your neyghe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bour, as ye woulde be done to?<note place="margin">Pſal. i. Deute. xii</note> Haue ye mercye and pite on the pore and nedye,<note place="margin">Math. vii. Roma. xii Eſay. i. Iames. i. Math, v.</note> the wydowe and orphane in the tyme of theyr ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſite? Can ye find in your har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes to loue youre enemies, and praye for them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> do you wronge? Stande ye ryghte vp in iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment lokynge nether to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ryghte hande nor to the lefte?<note place="margin">Leui. xix. Iere. xrii. Roma. vi</note> Kepe ye ſtyll the profeſſyon of your bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyme, forſakynge the deuil with all hys workes?<note place="margin">Luke. xii</note> Do ye ryſe whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> youre captaine doth cal &amp; are ye not in the ſlepe of vnryghtouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,
<pb facs="tcp:4681:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 75 -->and ſo fel into temptacion? Are ye obedient to goddes mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters,<note place="margin">1. Pet. ii.</note> the highe magiſtrates whiche doo ſupply here in ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the his mightie rome? And do ye walke allwayes in the feare of the Lorde,<note place="margin">Pſal. ii.</note> is his worde a lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne to youre fete, and a lighte vnto your doynges?</p>
            <p>¶ Now let this coroſiffe worke and take holde,<note place="margin">Ephe. iij.</note> and thinke whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther theſe thinge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſhalbe found wythin you. And thus too a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayte on your Capitayne Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſte as his faithful ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyours. But it is to be feared yf we ſearch the bottom of oure conſciences,<note place="margin">Luke. xii.</note> there ſhalbe founde packes full of iniquities wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chedneſſe and myſerye,<note place="margin">Pſal. v.</note> and all that leadethe vs to the open, mouthe of Hell, Menne naked wythoute armoure ouercome,<note place="margin">Math. vii. Apoca. ii</note> wyth euery larome, we maye be
<pb facs="tcp:4681:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 75 -->well callede freſhe water ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diours,<note place="margin">Mark. iiii</note> not able to, to abyde one ſtorme for oure lordes ſake,<note place="margin">ii. Cor. vi. Luk. xiiii pſa. cxxvii</note> we fall awaye with euerye tempeſt, when he bydeth vs for to abide, our manlines is torned i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to cow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ardnes, &amp; thus for ſake we our Lorde God but let vs remember what the holy prophete Dauid ſayeth, Lorde,<note place="margin">pſal. xxvii</note> (ſaith he) if y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> doeſt for ſake me, vnto whome ſhall I flee?<note place="margin">ii. Cor. iii.</note> If y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lorde do not kepe the cite in vayne do they watche y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> kepe it.<note place="margin">pſal. lxix</note> Lorde be thou oure tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, our caſtel &amp; our defence, loke doun fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heauen &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort thin ac<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> flicte. What at we withoute thy grace? Let vs loke round about vs wythin &amp; wythoute, &amp; we be compaſſed wythe ſinne.<note place="margin">i. Cor. iii Math. xxi</note> Thus in all Goodnes GOD gyuethe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> encreſe, but on out part wen ther plante nor water, we be the witheren fygge tree.<note place="margin">Luke. viij</note> Wee be the
<pb facs="tcp:4681:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 76 -->ſtony ground, no good frute can fructify,<note place="margin">Marke. vi.</note> we are baren voyde of all heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly grace, diſperſed as people wythout order.</p>
            <p>¶ O Chriſtenllyfe, which at the dredfull day ſhulde be our truſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes before our Lorde God,<note place="margin">Rom. viii</note> wher ſhall we fynd the? for the multy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of ſynnes ſhal couer vs, we may not for our iniquities be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde the high iudge to receyue hys Kyngdom,<note place="margin">Sapion. v.</note> but openly to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne oure ſelues, and receyue hys terryble iudgemente.<note place="margin">pſal. cxlv.</note> Who ſhall then ſtande forth to be iuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified by hys owne workes, or merytes?<note place="margin">ii. Pet. iii.</note> What ſhall we do, or what ſhall we ſaye in that terry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble day of vengeance, when hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and earthe ſhalbe altered? Who ſhalbe able to ſtande forth to pleade hys cauſe?<note place="margin">Eſay. liii.</note> And who ſhalbe able to ſtande by hymſelf all alone?<note place="margin">Math. xi.</note> Thus are wee preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb facs="tcp:4681:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 76 -->doune vnder the burden of ſinne, that ſcarcely we can taſte of God how pleaſant he is.</p>
            <p>But for ſo muche (good brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lorde is mercifull,<note place="margin">i. Petri. ii.</note> &amp; that hys mercy paſſethe all hys wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes,<note place="margin">Pſa. cxvii</note> for them that dothe beleue and repent, wyllyng to lay aſyde the clogge of ſynne, let vs wythe honor and glory magnyfy wyth ſoule and body oure immortall God &amp; euerlaſting lord,<note place="margin">i. Petri. ii.</note> acknow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledginge him to be the redemer and ſtole of grace, for all the ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the worlde.<note place="margin">Roma. iii.</note> And beſydes at all tymes where ſoeuer it be in Church felde or Towne me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and ſadde, to cary hym wythe vs in the ſpyrytuall partes of oure hartes, who hath promyſed to be wyth vs vnto thend of the world.<note place="margin">mat xxviii</note> Further in all our world<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly doynges to ſtande ryghte vp,<note place="margin">Math. vii.</note> and to do as we woulde be done
<pb facs="tcp:4681:7"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 77 -->reuerence to magnyfie hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> night and daye, for that the lawes of the Lorde doth appere,<note place="margin">Collo. iiii</note> hauynge theyre Conſciences pure in all their procedynges, permittynge vs (the pore ſubiectes) the lyber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of Chryſtes Goſpell,<note place="margin">Math. vi.</note> and the Heauenlye worde of hys God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head. For the whyche longe lyfe wythe the encreaſe of greate ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noure maye be vnto hym Deutrono. xxvii Let vs ſaye hartely.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:4681:7"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 77 -->
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
